Guide to the James R. Dumpson Papers circa 1922-2015 MS 3078
New-York Historical Society
- Series VIII. Print matter, 1922-2009; 6 Linear Feet
  - Sub-series VIII.B. Periodicals, 1955-2009; 0.75 Linear Feet
    - The Welfarer [published by the New York City Department of Welfare], vol. XI, 1959 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 13)
    - The Welfarer [published by the New York City Department of Welfare], vol. XII (2 copies), 1960 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 14-15)
    - The Welfarer [published by the New York City Department of Welfare], vol. XIII, 1961 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 16)
    - The Welfarer [published by the New York City Department of Welfare], vol. XIV, 1962 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 17)
    - The Welfarer [published by the New York City Department of Welfare], vol. XV, 1963 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 18)
  - Sub-series VIII.C. Government documents, 1951-1973; 0.50 Linear Feet
    - Civilian Casualty, Social Welfare, and Refugee Problems in South Vietnam. Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate Problems Connected With Refugees and Escapees of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Ninetieth Congress, First Session, 1967 May-October (Offsite-box 19, Folder 19)
    - Investigation of Organized Crime in Interstate Commerce. Hearings Before the Special Committee to Investigate Organized Crime in Interstate Commerce, United States Senate, Eighty-Second Congress, First Session, 1951 May-June (Offsite-box 19, Folder 20)
    - Juvenile Delinquency (New York Programs for the Prevention and Treatment of Juvenile Delinquency). Hearing Before the Subcommittee to Investigate Juvenile Delinquency of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Eighty-Fifth Congress, First Session, 1957 December 4 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 21)
    - Juvenile Delinquency. Report of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate (86th Cong., 2d Sess.) Made By its Subcommittee to Investigate Juvenile Delinquency, 1960 June 15 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 22)
    - Poverty in the United States. Committee on Education and Labor, House of Representatives, Eighty-Eighth Congress, Second Session, 1964 April (Offsite-box 19, Folder 23)
    - Relief and Rehabilitation of War Victims in Indochina. Part II: Orphans and Child Welfare. Hearing Before the Subcommittee to Investigate Problems Connected With Refugees and Escapees of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Ninety-Third Congress, First Session (3 copies), 1973 May 11 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 24)
    - Relief and Rehabilitation of War Victims in Indochina. Part IV: South Vietnam and Regional Problems. Hearing Before the Subcommittee to Investigate Problems Connected With Refugees and Escapees of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Ninety-Third Congress, First Session (2 copies), 1973 August 1 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 25)
    - Report of Findings of Special Review of Aid to Families With Dependent Children in New York City. Transmitted to the Committee on Ways and Means by the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and the New York State Department of Social Services (2 copies), 1969 September 24 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 26)
  - Sub-series VIII.D. Hardbound publications, 1922-1992; 1 Linear Feet
    - Beyond Homelessness: Frames of Reference | Benedict Giamo and Jeffrey Grunberg, 1992 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 1)
      Includes interview, "The Social Welfare: James R. Dumpson."
    - Competition and Compassion: Conflicting Roles for Public Hospitals | Stuart H. Altman et al., eds, 1989 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 2)
    - Evaluation of Social Intervention | Edward J. Mullen, James R. Dumpson, et al, 1972 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 3)
    - Fifty Years of Care, 1918-1968. State of New Jersey, Department of Institutions and Agencies. Golden Anniversary Edition., 1968 December (Offsite-box 20, Volume 4)
    - Jamshed Nusserwanjee: A Memorial (Karachi: The Jamshed Memorial Volume Committee), 1954 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 5)
      Jamshed Nusserwanjee Mehta (1886-1952) was the first elected mayor of Karachi, Pakistan. Volume inscribed to Dumpson by the members of the Social Services Coordinating Council, 1956.
    - Profiles in Social Work | Mary L. Gottefeld and Mary E. Pharis (2 copies), 1977 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 6.1, 6.2)
      Chapter 7, interview with James R. Dumpson.
    - Profiles of African Leaders | Thomas Patrick Melady, 1961 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 7)
    - Psychotherapy in Child Guidance | Gordon Hamilton, 1947 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 8)
    - Reir y Aprender [Laugh and Learn] | Miguel Gabriel, 1941 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 9)
    - The Renaissance: Studies in Art and Poetry | Walter Pater, 1922 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 10)
    - Social Security in International Perspective: Essays in Honor of Eveline M. Burns | Shirley Jenkins, ed, 1969 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 11)
    - Theory and Practice of Social Case Work. 2nd edition | Gordon Hamilton, 1951 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 12)
    - Volta: Man's Greatest Lake | James Moxon, 1969 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 13)
      Lake Volta, in Ghana, is the largest artificial reservoir in the world.
    - Working with Teen-Age Gangs: A Report on the Central Harlem Street Clubs Project | Paul L. Crawford et. al. (3 copies), 1950 (Offsite-box 20, Volume 14.1, 14.2, 14.3)
  - Sub-series VIII.E. Proceedings of the National Conference of Social Work, 1939-1981; 2 Linear Feet
    - Proceedings of the National Conference of Social Work. Selected Papers, Sixty-Sixth Annual Conference, Buffalo, New York (2 copies), 1939 June 18–24 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 1.1, 1.2)
    - Proceedings of the National Conference of Social Work. Selected Papers, Sixty-Eighth Annual Conference, Atlantic City, New Jersey (2 copies), 1941 June 1–7 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 2.1, 2.2)
    - Proceedings of the National Conference of Social Work. Selected Papers, Seventy-Fifth Anniversary Meeting, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1948 April 17–23 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 3)
    - The Social Welfare Forum. Official Proceedings, 76th Annual Meeting, National Conference of Social Work, Cleveland, Ohio, 1949 June 12–17 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 4)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1950. Official Proceedings, 77th Annual Meeting, National Conference of Social Work, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1950 April 23–28 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 5)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1951. Official Proceedings, 78th Annual Meeting, National Conference of Social Work, Atlantic City, New Jersey (2 copies), 1951 May 13–18 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 6.1, 6.2)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1958. Official Proceedings, 85th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Chicago, Illinois, 1958 May 11–16 (Offsite-box 21, Volume 7)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1961. Official Proceedings, 88th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1961 May 14–19 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 1)
      Include James R. Dumpson, "Hunger and Human Welfare."
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1962. Official Proceedings, 89th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, New York, New York, 1962 May 27–June 1 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 2)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1963. Official Proceedings, 90th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Cleveland, Ohio, 1963 May 19–24 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 3)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1966. Official Proceedings, 93d Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Chicago, Illinois, 1966 May 29–June 3 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 4)
    - Social Work Practice, 1967. Selected Papers, 94th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Dallas, Texas, 1967 May 21–26 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 5)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1968. Official Proceedings, 95th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, San Francisco, California, 1968 May 26–31 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 6)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1969. Official Proceedings, 96th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, New York, New York, 1969 May 25–29 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 7)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1970. Official Proceedings, 97th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Chicago, Illinois (2 copies), 1970 May 31–June 5 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 8.1, 8.2)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1971. Official Proceedings, 98th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Dallas, Texas, 1971 May 16–21 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 9)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1972. Official Proceedings, 99th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Chicago, Illinois, 1972 May 28–June 2 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 10)
      Includes frontispiece portrait of Dumpson and his paper "Breaking the Barriers to an Open Society." For correspondence and other documentation of the controversy surrounding the location of this conference, which was originally planned for Anaheim, California, but switched to Chicago, see box 13, folders 5-6.
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1973. Official Proceedings, 100th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1973 May 27–31 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 11)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1975. Official Proceedings, 102d Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, San Francisco, California (2 copies), 1975 May 11–15 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 12.1, 12.2)
      Includes James R. Dumpson's response to Melvin A. Glaser's "Health as a Right: The Human and Political Dimensions."
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1976. Official Proceedings, 103d Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Washington, D.C., 1976 June 13–17 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 13)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1977. Official Proceedings, 104th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, Chicago, Illinois, 1977 May 15–18 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 14)
    - The Social Welfare Forum, 1981. Official Proceedings, 108th Annual Forum, National Conference on Social Welfare, San Francisco, California, 1981 June 7–10 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 15)
- Series IX. Audiovisual, 1946-1992; 0.82 Linear Feet
  Phonograph and VHS recordings of appearances by James R. Dumpson on New York City-based radio and television programs discussing topics such as juvenile delinquency, the AIDS crisis, and homelessness.
  Series IX is organized in two sub-series:
  Sub-series IX.A. Phonograph records, 1946-1965
  Sub-series IX.B. VHS tapes, 1984-1992
  Items are sorted chronologically within each sub-series.
  - Sub-series IX.A. Phonograph records, 1946-1965; 0.41 Linear Feet
    Access Restrictions
    The phonograph records are restricted because of their fragility and because N-YHS has no equipment on which to play them.
    - [10-inch] New York Post. Learn-A-Language Record Course: Spanish. (4 discs + 4 manuals), 1946, 1955 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-5)
    - [12-inch] Campus Press Conference (2 discs), 1959 September-October (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
      Labeled "DATE OF PROGRAM 9-20-59 / DATE RECORDED: 10-28-59."
    - [10-inch] Metropolitan Probe, WNEW-TV, 1959 November 15 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [12-inch] Direct Line, NBC-TV, 1960 July 17 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    - [12-inch] The Searchlight, NBC-TV, 1960 July 17 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    - [10-inch] The Searchlight, NBC-TV, 1961 March 5 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [12-inch] The Searchlight, NBC-TV, 1962 January 28 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
    - [10-inch] City Close-Up, WNYC, 1963 December 1 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Let's Find Out, CBS, 1964 January 5 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] The Searchlight, NBC-TV, 1964 January 12 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Let's Find Out, CBS, 1964 July 12 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Community Dialogue, WNEW-TV, 1964 August 2 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Radio Press Conference, ABC, 1965 January 3 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Page One, ABC-TV, 1965 January 10 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] Let's Find Out, CBS, 1965 January 17 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] J.R. Dumpson, Arthur Clinton on Delinquency, undated (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
    - [10-inch] J. Dumpson interviewed on narcotic drugs, undated (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series IX.B. VHS tapes, 1984-1992; 0.41 Linear Feet
    The VHS tapes are restricted because of their fragility and because N-YHS has no equipment on which to play them.
    - New York Close-Up, 1984 April 12 (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 1)
    - Meeting the Challenge of AIDS: Funding in the 1990s (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 2)
    - Dr. Dumpson—News Forum Four w/Gabe Pressman, WNBC, 1991 December 8 (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 3)
    - Dr. Jim Dumpson CBS re Hospitals w/Jim Jensen, 1991 Fall (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 4)
    - "NY Medical College Ceremony JRD Honored 11/9/92" OR "Channel 13 Presentation re: GAYS", 1992 November 9 (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 5)
    - Conversation on the Homeless, undated (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 6)
    - David Diaz, NBC News, Kings County Hospital Center: In Critical Condition and Trauma of the City, undated (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 7)
    - The City (taped thru?), undated (Offsite-box 24, Cassette 8)